So the Nigerian Code of Copy Governance, just
to speak to it a little bit, is
a code of best practise.
It has 28 principles and the idea behind
it, the philosophy behind it, is apply and
explain.
So essentially, apply the principles and each principle
also has guidelines or best practise on how
to apply those principles.
Indeed, whilst it's apply and explain, the Financial
Reporting Council, which is the one that has
the custody of ensuring compliance, has also introduced
sanctions for non-compliance with the provisions of
the code.
So I'll just quickly go through a few
provisions of the respective codes and guidelines as
to what they say with regards to certain
key governance principles or issues.
The first one I will speak to is
the board size.
So the Nigerian Code of Copy Governance has
not mandated a particular number of directors to
be on the board and it has left
it to the discretion of the board or
the board charter to determine how many directors
can effectively oversee the activities of the business.
However, sectoral codes have in their wisdom defined
minimum and maximum numbers.
So for instance, the CBN Code of Copy
Governance provides for a minimum number of seven
directors and a maximum number of 15 directors
on the board of the commercial bank.
So on board composition, the codes require that
the three types of directors that we had
described earlier on should be on the board,
with each guideline or code also requiring that
there should be a minimum of at least
one independent non-executive director on the board.
The CBN code is stricter as it requires
that there should be at least three independent
directors on the board of the bank, one
of whom shall have knowledge and expertise in
innovation, financial technology, information communication technology, and
cyber security.
The codes also speak to the codes and
guidelines.
I will use codes and guidelines interchangeably in
the course of this session.
So the codes also speak to more diversity
and diversity has been clearly defined to not
just be gender diversity, but also diversity in
terms of age, experience, background, and all the
general principles of diversity including ethnic diversity.
Not all the codes have defined tenure for
directors like I said earlier on.
So the Nigerian Code of Copy Governance has
left this at the discretion of the board,
but the CBN code and CBN guidelines is
quite strict on tenure and has defined a
maximum of 12 years for executive and non
-executive directors, and eight years for independent non
-executive directors.
The rationale for defining tenure is to ensure
that the board periodically has an opportunity to
refresh its membership such that we don't have
the same directors serving for inordinate periods of
time.
Gone are the days where directors are appointed
and they understand that their appointments are for
life as our trustees.
However, directors should have fixed tenure, like I
said, to ensure that the board continues to
refresh itself and replenish its membership.